<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Pyrefly Blog</title>
        <link>https://pyrefly.org/blog/</link>
        <description>Pyrefly Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Pyrefly - A new type checker and IDE experience for Python]]></title>
            <link>https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/</link>
            <guid>https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Today we are announcing an alpha version of Pyrefly, an open source Python typechecker and IDE extension crafted in Rust]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Pyrefly Intro" src="https://pyrefly.org/assets/images/pyrefly_intro-29fb0e2d54b79ced50ee1065dc4a2a4d.webp" width="2242" height="1260" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Today we are announcing an alpha version of Pyrefly, an open source Python typechecker and IDE extension crafted in Rust. Pyrefly is a static type checker that analyzes Python code to ensure type consistency and help you catch errors throughout your codebase before your code runs. It also supports IDE integration and CLI usage to give you flexibility in how you incorporate it into your workflow.</p>
<p>The open source community is the backbone of the Python language. We are eager to collaborate on Pyrefly with the community and improve Python’s type system and the many libraries that we all rely on.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="get-started">Get started<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#get-started" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Get started" title="Direct link to Get started">​</a></h2>
<p>Ready to dive in? The <a href="https://pyrefly.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">official Pyrefly website</a> has all the details, but to quickly get started:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pyrefly.org/en/docs/installation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Install</a> Pyrefly on the command-line: pip install pyrefly.</li>
<li><a href="https://pyrefly.org/en/docs/migrating-to-pyrefly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Migrate your existing type checker configuration to Pyrefly</a>.</li>
<li>Enhance Your IDE: Download the <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=meta.pyrefly" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pyrefly extension for VSCode</a> and enjoy a lightning fast IDE experience from starter projects to monorepos.</li>
<li>Leave feedback for us on <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-we-built-pyrefly">Why we built Pyrefly<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#why-we-built-pyrefly" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why we built Pyrefly" title="Direct link to Why we built Pyrefly">​</a></h2>
<p>Back in 2017, we embarked on a mission to create a type checker that could handle <a href="https://instagram-engineering.com/web-service-efficiency-at-instagram-with-python-4976d078e366" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram’s massive codebas</a> of typed Python. This mission led to the birth of the <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyre-check" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pyre</a> type checker, inspired by the robust designs of <a href="https://hacklang.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hack</a> and <a href="https://flow.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Flow</a>, and written in OCaml to deliver scalable performance.</p>
<p>Over the years, Pyre served us well, but as the type system evolved and the need for typechecking to drive responsive IDE emerged, it was clear that we needed to take a new approach. We explored alternate solutions and leveraged community tools like <a href="https://github.com/Microsoft/pyright" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pyright</a> for code navigation. But the need for an extensible type checker that can bring code navigation, checking at scale, and exporting types to other services drove us to start over, creating Pyrefly.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-principles-behind-pyrefly">The principles behind Pyrefly<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#the-principles-behind-pyrefly" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The principles behind Pyrefly" title="Direct link to The principles behind Pyrefly">​</a></h2>
<p>Today, we’re excited to unveil Pyrefly, a project <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">we’ve been developing openly on GitHub</a>. We invite you to explore our work and try it out on your own project. While a project like Pyrefly is the sum of thousands of technical choices, a few notable principles we’ve followed are:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="performance">Performance<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#performance" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Performance" title="Direct link to Performance">​</a></h3>
<p>We want to shift checks that used to happen later on CI to happening on every single keystroke. That requires checking code at speed (on large codebases we can check 1.8 million lines of code per second!) and careful thought to incrementality and updates. Pyrefly is implemented in Rust and designed for high performance on codebases of all sizes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ide-first">IDE first<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#ide-first" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to IDE first" title="Direct link to IDE first">​</a></h3>
<p>We want the IDE and command line to share a consistent view of the world, which means crafting abstractions that capture the differences without incurring unnecessary costs. Designing these abstractions from the beginning is much easier than retrofitting them, which we tried with Pyre.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="inference">Inference<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#inference" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Inference" title="Direct link to Inference">​</a></h3>
<p>Some <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2024/12/09/developer-tools/typed-python-2024-survey-meta/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Python programs are typed</a>, but many aren’t. We want users to benefit from types even if they haven’t annotated their code – so automatically infer types for returns and local variables and display them in the IDE. What’s more, in the IDE you can even double click to insert these inferred types if you think that would make the program better.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="open-source">Open source<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#open-source" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Open source" title="Direct link to Open source">​</a></h3>
<p>Python is open source, and hugely popular. The <a href="https://typing.python.org/en/latest/spec/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Python typing specification</a> is open source, which made Pyrefly vastly easier to develop. Many of the libraries Meta contributes to are open source,( e.g., <a href="https://pytorch.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PyTorch</a>).</p>
<p>Pyrefly is also open source, <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">available on GitHub</a> under the <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/blob/main/LICENSE" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MIT license</a>, and we encourage <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/pulls" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pull requests</a> and <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">issue reports</a>. We also have a <a href="https://discord.gg/Cf7mFQtW7W" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord channel</a> for more free flowing discussions. We would love to build a community around Pyrefly.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-future-of-pyrefly">The future of Pyrefly<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#the-future-of-pyrefly" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The future of Pyrefly" title="Direct link to The future of Pyrefly">​</a></h2>
<p>We will work with the Python community to drive the language forward and improve the developer experience. Since the beginning of Pyre, we open sourced our code and contributed a number of PEPs alongside the community of type checker maintainers. We feel we can do more with Pyrefly to help Python developers leverage the benefits of types for developers, library authors, and folks just learning the language.</p>
<p>Meta has leveraged types in dynamic languages from the beginning and knows the significant benefits it brings to developer productivity and security. We plan to share more of our learnings and tooling with <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2024/12/09/developer-tools/typed-python-2024-survey-meta/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">blogs</a>, better types in the ecosystem and language enhancements.</p>
<p>Today we’re releasing Pyrefly as an alpha. At the same time, we’re busy burning down the long-tail of bugs and features aiming to remove the alpha label this Summer. Your feedback is invaluable to get there, so please give it a try and <a href="https://github.com/facebook/pyrefly/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">report your bugs</a> or things you think can be improved. Even if Pyrefly isn’t right for your project, we would love to hear how you use types and what you would like to see improved in your editor.</p>
<p>Join us on the journey as we help illuminate your bugs with Pyrefly. Happy coding! 🐍✨</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hear-more-about-pyrefly">Hear more about Pyrefly<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#hear-more-about-pyrefly" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Hear more about Pyrefly" title="Direct link to Hear more about Pyrefly">​</a></h2>
<p>Check out the <a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2025/05/15/developer-tools/open-sourcing-pyrefly-a-faster-python-type-checker-written-in-rust" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">episode of the Meta Tech Podcast</a> where several team members share their experience developing Pyrefly and technical details for how it works. We also just <a href="https://us.pycon.org/2025/schedule/presentation/118/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">talked at PyCon US</a> about high-performance Python through faster type checking and free threaded execution.</p>
<p>To learn more about Meta Open Source, visit our<a href="https://opensource.fb.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open source site</a>, subscribe to our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCCQY962PmHabTjaHv2wJzfQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">YouTube channel</a>, or follow us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/MetaOpenSource" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://www.threads.net/@metaopensource" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Threads</a>, <a href="https://x.com/MetaOpenSource" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">X</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/meta-open-source?fbclid=IwZXh0bgNhZW0CMTEAAR2fEOJNb7zOi8rJeRvQry5sRxARpdL3OpS4sYLdC1_npkEy60gBS1ynXwQ_aem_mJUK6jEUApFTW75Emhtpqw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements<a href="https://pyrefly.org/blog/introducing-pyrefly/#acknowledgements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Acknowledgements" title="Direct link to Acknowledgements">​</a></h3>
<p><em>Pyrefly was created By Meta’s Python Language Tooling Team: Jia Chen, Rebecca Chen, Sam Goldman, David Luo, Kyle Into, Zeina Migeed, Neil Mitchell, Maggie Moss, Conner Nilsen, Aaron Pollack, Teddy Sudol, Steven Troxler, Lucian Wischik, Danny Yang, and Sam Zhou.</em></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>typechecking</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>